Guide to the Oral Histories Documenting Yale University Women
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Ameling, Ann, 2008 June 27; Accession 2012-A-036
  Ameling recalls her early experiences in the Berkeley College fellowship, how gradually she became involved in university administration, and the role diversity initiatives played in providing opportunities for her advancement. An account is given of the difficulties she experienced, both as a woman and as a member of the Nursing School, in chairing her first university committee. Looking back on her time as Acting Master at Berkeley and Master of Saybrook, she describes the challenges of these positions, and the extent to which her gender complicated them. Her time in Yale's central administration, which culminated in her seven years as associate provost, is then discussed. She recalls her relationships with Provosts Frank Turner, Judith Rodin and Alison Richard, as well as gender and power relations within the Provost's Office. Ameling outlines the pressures involved in managing her diverse responsibilities, especially at a time of economic stringency, and the battle to prevent the closure of the Nursing and Divinity schools. She describes the evolution of Yale's retirement and maternity policies, explaining her role in the implementation of the Yale family leave policy and domestic partner benefit plan, the ways in which being a woman influenced her position on these issues, and her own maternity and childcare arrangements. The role gender played in the development of her management style, and the nature of her own feminist sensibility, are covered. Ameling discusses how salary inequities, the abolition of mandatory retirement, and Yale's tenure system, affected younger faculty, particularly women. In this context she talks about her commitment to the mentoring of young faculty and administrators.
  Ameling then explains why she left the central administration, giving an account of the personal costs she believed she incurred, and identifying what she regards as her greatest achievements as assistant provost. Next she turns to her second period on the YSN faculty and her struggle to find a new direction in her scholarship and teaching. Finally, she talks about her decision to become a student at the Yale Divinity School (including her experience of being a student again), and shares her views on the current situation of women in the academy and changing perceptions of the role of the university in society.
  - Audiorecording, 3; ; 4 hours and 55 minutes
    - Use copy, 1
  - Edited transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1)
- Borroff, Marie, 2008 January 31; Accession 2012-A-037
  Marie Borroff was born on September 10, 1923, in New York City. She completed high school at the age of fifteen, after which she spent a year studying piano at the Chicago Conservatory and some time earning a living playing the piano in New York. She earned her undergraduate and master's degrees at the University of Chicago, where she won the James Billings Fiske poetry prize in 1943. Before coming to Yale for her Ph.D. in English Literature and Philology, which she completed in 1956, she was a teaching assistant at the University of Chicago, 1946-1947, and then an instructor in English at Smith College, 1948-1951. After completing her Ph.D. Borroff returned to Smith as an Assistant Professor, and then Associate Professor, from 1956-1959. In 1959, she became the first woman to teach in the English Department at Yale, and in 1965 she became the first woman to be appointed as tenured Professor of English, and only the second woman to be tenured in the Faculty of Arts and Sciences at the university. In 1991, she became the first woman on the faculty to be named a Sterling Professor. Marie Borroff retired in 1994.
  During her forty years on the Yale faculty, Marie Borroff held many administrative and committee positions, most notably Faculty Counselor to the Presidential Search Committee, 1992-1993, in which she was charged with relaying the views of the faculty to the committee. In 1984 she served as wordsmith for the seminal Crothers Report of the Faculty of Arts and Sciences Advisory Committee on the Education of Women at Yale.
  Marie Borroff's varied scholarly interests encompass the poetry of both the Middle Ages and the twentieth century. In 1963, she published Wallace Stevens: a Collection of Critical Essays (Prentice-Hall) and Language and the Poet: Verbal Artistry in Frost, Stevens, and Moore (University of Chicago Press, 1979). She has translated three works by the so-called Gawain or Pearl-poet, Patience, Pearl, and Sir Gawain and the Green Knight (Norton, 2001), and is the author of two major collections of critical essays on the subject, Sir Gawain and the Green Knight: a Stylistic and Metrical Study (Yale University Press, 1963) and Traditions and Renewals: Chaucer, the Gawain-poet and Beyond (Yale University Press, 2003). Her translations of the remaining two Pearl-poet works, Cleanness and St. Erkenwald, will appear in 2008. Her own collected poems, Stars and Other Signs, were published by Yale University Press in 2002. In 1995 she was honored by a festschrift, The Endless Knot: Essays on Old and Middle English in Honor of Marie Borroff, edited by M. Teresa Tavormina and R. F. Yeager (Boydell and Brewer, 1995). A distinguished teacher, her lectures were filmed for the Yale Great Teachers Series. She was on the board of Yale University Press, 1988-1998, and the Yale University Alumni Association awarded her the Wilbur Cross Medal, the highest honor of the Yale Graduate School, in 1996.
  In January 2008, Yale University established the Marie Borroff Professor of English in her honor. Its first recipient is another woman and a fellow-medievalist, Roberta Frank.
  Marie Borroff begins by talking about the newly established Marie Borroff Professorship and its significance to her. She pays tribute to her upbringing, especially how her father, a man of little formal education, encouraged independence and intellectual excellence, against the prevailing attitudes on the education of women. Her mother was a talented pianist and from their earliest childhood playing the piano was a daily discipline for Borroff and her sister. She recounts her early discovery of poetry and the role of music in her life, both as a source of income as a young woman, and as an inspiration in her literary scholarship. Borroff recalls the social and intellectual challenges of her student years at the University of Chicago, its unique Ph.B. (Bachelor of Philosophy) undergraduate program, and the influence and mentorship of two Chicago teachers, Norman Maclean and R. S. Crane. Life as a graduate student at Yale is described: her experience of living in the women's dormitory; her relationships with other graduate students including E. D. Hirsch; and how she was mentored by her exclusively male teachers, Helge Kokeritz, John C. Pope and E. Talbot Donaldson. Borroff talks at length about the social expectations of women at Smith College especially the Ivy League "mixer" culture, and the effect of that culture on the first cohort of women undergraduates at Yale. Borroff remembers how she got her first job at Yale, how she secured tenure and what it was like to teach male undergraduates. Much is said about the intellectual and social culture of the Yale English Department, her male colleagues and their wives, and her experience of being the only woman in the department for many years. Borroff recalls her encounters with the sinologist Mary Clabaugh Wright, the only other tenured woman in the Faculty of Arts and Sciences at that time. The arrival of the first junior female faculty in the mid-1960s is addressed, and the extent to which gender became a complicating issue in the historic division between junior and senior faculty at Yale. Borroff talks about her experiences of mentoring the younger, junior women faculty, and her attempts to ameliorate what she considers to be the exploitation of several of them. She describes her involvement in the Helen Hadley Hall Fellowship for women at Yale, and how she became a Fellow at Ezra Stiles College. She discusses her work on the 1984 Crothers Report on the education of women at Yale; her views on co-education; feminism, discrimination and affirmative action at Yale; the challenges she faced as an interim Director of Graduate Studies; her contribution to the Presidential Search Committee, 1992-1993; and why she did not pursue an administrative career at Yale. Finally Borroff considers the changing role of the humanities in American culture, and the growing place of women in academia.
  - Audiorecording, 4; ; 4 hours and 15 minutes
    - Use copy, 1
  - Edited transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1)
- Doane, Winifred, 2009 June 3; Accession 2012-A-038
  Winifred W. Doane was born on January 7, 1929, and raised on City Island, New York. Her parents were educators and firm advocates of women's education: her father a founding member of the School of Architecture at City College, and her mother a special education teacher for many years on Manhattan's Lower East Side. A talented all-rounder at Walton High School in the Bronx, Doane was inspired by her science teacher to major in science at university. She graduated from Hunter College in 1950 with a B.A. in zoology and botany, winning many of the science prizes. In 1952, she gained a M.S. in Zoology and Genetics at the University of Wisconsin, Madison. She began her doctoral studies there but married a fellow graduate student, Charles "Chuck" Doane the following year when he completed his Ph.D. Their early married life was somewhat peripatetic as Doane's husband established his career, but they had also agreed that once they settled Doane would continue her doctoral studies. Consequently, she taught at Millsaps College, Mississippi, for two years, then at Washington University, St. Louis, before coming to New Haven, Connecticut. where Chuck Doane took a position at the Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station. Winifred Doane enrolled on the Yale Ph.D. program, graduating in 1960. The Doanes adopted a baby son in 1965.
  During nearly twenty years at Yale, Winifred Doane held a number of appointments: laboratory teaching assistant in Zoology (1956-1958), National Science Foundation Predoctoral Research Fellow (1958-1960), National Institutes of Health Postdoctoral Trainee in Genetics (1960-1962), Faculty Research Associate, Biology (1962-1975) and Lecturer, Biology (1965-1975). She was one of the early test cases in which the newly established Yale Affirmative Action office attempted to have a number of Yale's longstanding women scientists promoted into faculty ladder positions in order to give them the possibility of tenure. This resulted in Doane's promotion to Associate Professor, Biology (1975-1977). Doane's husband retired soon after this, leaving her free to apply for a tenured position elsewhere. She was appointed Professor of Zoology at Arizona State University in 1977, and then Professor, Molecular/Cell Biology, in 1992. She retired in 1998.
  Winifred Doane specialized in the developmental, biochemical and molecular genetics of Drosophila (fruit flies) and other insects. One of her major discoveries was to identify the "skinny gene" (adipose). She was the recipient of many research grants from the National Institutes of Health and the National Science Foundation throughout her academic life. She is the author of more than 120 research papers and articles related to her work. A major review chapter on the role of hormones in insect development was contributed to S.J. Counce & C.H. Waddington's Developmental Systems: Insects (Academic Press. 1972).
  Active in the Association of Women Scientists (AWIS) from its inception, she was also the founder and first president of the Central Arizona Chapter of AWIS. Doane is an American Association for the Advancement of Science Fellow. In 2009, AWIS, in conjunction with AAAS, honored her for her "commitment to the achievement of equity for women in science, technology, engineering and mathematics." Doane's service to the scientific community at a national level included being Chair of the Responsibilities Committee of the Society for Developmental Biology, 1971-1974, during which time she produced "Sexisms Satirized," a humorous book of cartoons highlighting sexism in science; she was also a member of the Congressional Liaison Committee of the Genetics Society of America, 1993-1995. Doane was a founding council member of the ASU Emeritus College, which was established in 2004 and continued to be particularly active in its mentoring program for young faculty.
  Winifred Doane begins her interview with an account of her family and educational background and the formative experiences which shaped her early life. She talks extensively about her mother's work and familial attitudes to women's education and careers, going on to reflect on her undergraduate years at Hunter College and the beginnings of her postgraduate education at the University of Wisconsin at Madison. Doane recalls the graduate culture there and how she met her future husband. Negotiating marriage and motherhood to enable her to achieve her own academic and professional ambitions is a recurrent theme in the interview.
  Most of the interview is devoted to the twenty years she spent at Yale. Doane recalls various ways in which Yale was a challenging environment for women scientists, and recounts many personal experiences of sexism and discrimination, whilst, at the same time acknowledging the support and mentorship of a number of her male colleagues, like Donald Poulson and Evelyn Hutchinson whom she found supportive and respectful. She reflects to what extent the ways in which the cultural attitudes of Yale's scientists towards women in science mirrored attitudes in the scientific world at large. An account is given of what she encountered at the National Science Foundation and the National Institutes of Health, especially in respect of grant applications she made in the late 1960s and early 1970s. She also recalls how what she regards as the then structural sexism in the science establishment also affected her husband's career because of the fact he had a working wife. The issue of tenure at Yale had particular difficulties for women, as she then explains, recounting in detail how they were addressed in the early years of Affirmative Action at Yale. Thus a context is provided for her own tenure experience. Doane outlines the circumstances of her resignation from Yale and her move to Arizona State University, reflecting on both the losses and gains she experienced in terms of her career by leaving Yale. Then she explains how her experiences at Yale influenced how she conducted her academic life after she left, and affirms her lasting commitment to mentoring young women scientists.
  Doane charts her growing awareness of feminist issues in the late 60s and the ambivalence she found amongst both male and female colleagues towards affirmative action. She explains how she became involved in the Association of Women in Science (AWIS) and other scientific bodies in the early 1970s, and her commitment to raising awareness of sexism and discrimination through them. These early involvements culminated in the publication of "Sexisms Satirized" in 1976. Finally, she shares her views on and impressions of the new generation of women scientists' prospects in academic life, addressing the issue of how women are changing the academy and how it is changing them, in the wider context of how science itself is changing.
  - Audiorecording, 3; ; 3 hours and 31 mintes
    - Use copy, 1
  - Edited transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1)
- Eisenstein, Hester, 2008 May 21; Accession 2012-A-039
  Permission to access must be obtained from interviewee until January 1, 2040.
  Hester Eisenstein was born October 14, 1940, in New York City into an upper middle class, intellectual, Jewish family. In 1961 she graduated from Radcliffe College with a B.A. ( magna cum laude ). The following year she earned a M.A. from Yale, where she also took her Ph.D. (in 1967). She won the Mary Cady Tew prize for the best first year graduate student in 1961. She taught history at Yale from 1966-1970, as an instructor for the first two years and subsequently as an assistant professor.
  After she left Yale, she was hired as Director of the Experimental College at Barnard College where (in 1975) she introduced its first course on feminist theory and (in 1977) co-founded the Women's Studies program. In 1980, Eisenstein moved to Sydney, Australia, for personal reasons. From 1980-1988, she was a "femocrat" (a female senior civil servant), working from 1981-1985 in the Office of the Director of Equal Opportunity in Public Employment in New South Wales implementing a government-funded affirmative action program for aboriginal Australians, immigrants and women. During 1985-1988 she was chief education officer in the Equal Employment Opportunity Unit at the Department of Education of New South Wales.
  On her return to the United States she worked as an associate professor in American Studies and Women's Studies at the State University of New York, Buffalo. From 1996-2000 she served as Director of Women's Studies at Queens College, City University of New York, where she is a professor of Sociology.
  In addition to many articles in journals and anthologies, Eisenstein's major publications include: The Future of Difference (edited with Alice Jardine, G.K. Hall, 1980); Contemporary Feminist Thought (G.K. Hall, 1983); Gender Shock: Practicing Feminism on Two Continents (Beacon, 1991); Inside Agitators: Australian Femocrats and the State (Temple University Press, 1996), and Feminism Seduced: How Global Elites Use Women's Labor and Ideas to Exploit the World (Paradigm Books, 2009).
  Hester Eisenstein discusses her family background and how it influenced her choice of profession, touching on her undergraduate experience at Radcliffe and the differences between Yale and Harvard in the teaching of history. She recalls encounters with Hannah Gray (later Yale's first female Provost) when Gray was on the faculty at Harvard, and with the historian, Mary Clabaugh Wright, who was the first woman to be tenured in Yale College. She speaks at length about the challenge of being one of the few women graduate students in the History Department, and her relationship with such Yale historians as Robin Winks, Stanley Mellon, John Blum and C. Vann Woodward. A lengthy account is given of the prevailing culture of Yale in general and the history department in particular, and how research in France (and subsequently the arrival of co-education in 1969 and the events surrounding May Day, 1970) enabled her, as a young faculty member, to articulate her growing socialist and feminist consciousness in her teaching practice as well as in her intellectual and political engagements. Eisenstein discusses her association with African-American students like Armstead Robinson, and explores the extent to which women's issues were part of political activism at Yale, touching on her friendship with feminist, Naomi Weisstein. She describes being on the Yale College Executive Committee during this period, considers the effect of the Yale tenure system on young faculty, and speculates on why she was denied tenure. She recalls how Elga Wasserman was instrumental in her being hired by Barnard College to run its new experimental college. Her first encounter with the contemporary feminist movement is described, together with her role in pioneering a feminist curriculum at Barnard, where she developed the Women's Studies program in association with feminist historians like Anne Kar Baxter. She recalls the first The Scholar and The Feminist Conference and the first National Women's Studies Association conference in 1977. In the context of her experience as a senior civil servant in Australia, she explores the term "femocrat" and the role of feminism in Australian public policy in the 1980s. Her interview concludes with a critique of contemporary American academic feminism and the future of Women's Studies in the context of 21st century globalization.
  - Audiorecording, 1; ; 2 hours and 5 minutes
    - Use copy, 1
  - Edited transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1)
- Farley, Margaret, 2009 February 10; Accession 2012-A-040
  Margaret Farley was born in 1935 and brought up in St. Cloud, Minnesota, in a Roman Catholic family. Her father taught at St. John's University in St. Joseph. Her mother had a college education but was a homemaker until the children were raised, when she took a degree in guidance counseling and became a fulltime counselor at a local high school. Farley took a B.A. in English at the University of Detroit in 1957, and a M.A. in Philosophy there in 1960. She entered the order of the Sisters of Mercy at the age of 24, and taught philosophy at the Mercy College in Detroit for five years from 1962-1967. By this time Farley knew that she wanted to commit to the academic life, so in 1967 she came to Yale to pursue a doctorate in the Religious Studies department. She graduated in 1973.
  Margaret Farley began her teaching career at Yale in 1971, when she became the first woman to serve fulltime on the faculty of Yale Divinity School. At the same time, she and Henri Nouwen became the first Roman Catholic faculty appointments at the school. She taught Christian Ethics at Yale for more than 30 years, as a lecturer 1971-1972, Assistant Professor, 1972-1974 and Associate Professor 1974-1984. In 1986 she was appointed to the Gilbert L. Stark Chair in Christian Ethics, and in 2007 she retired.
  Her honors include eleven honorary degrees, the John Courtney Murray Award for Excellence in Theology, and a Luce Fellowship in Theology. Farley is a past president of the Society of Christian Ethics and the Catholic Theological Society of America. She was a founder of the "Project on Gender, Faith, and Responses to HIV/AIDS." In addition to being a co-director of the Yale University Interdisciplinary Bioethics Project, she served on the Bioethics Committee of Yale-New Haven Hospital and the Ethics Committee of the American Society of Reproductive Medicine.
  Farley has been a progressive theological voice in many spheres, including feminist theology, ethics and spirituality, medical ethics, women's ordination, sexuality, and the environment. She has written more than eighty articles addressing such issues and is also the author and co-author of several books, including: A Metaphysics of Being and God (Prentice-Hall, 1966), Personal Commitments: Beginning, Keeping, Changing (Harper & Row, 1986), Embodiment, Morality, and Medicine (co-edited with L. Cahill; Kluwer, 1995), Readings in Moral Theology, No. 9: Feminist Ethics and the Catholic Moral Tradition (Paulist Press, 1996), Liberating Eschatology: Essays in Honor of Letty M. Russell (co-edited with Serene Jones; Westminster/John Knox, 1999), Compassionate Respect: A Feminist Approach to Medical Ethics (Paulist Press, 2002), and Just Love: A Framework for a Christian Sexual Ethic (Continuum, 2002). Just Love won the 2008 Grawemeyer Award in Religion. Her work was honored at a Yale Divinity School conference in 2005 entitled "Just Love: feminism, theology and ethics in a global context," and by a Festschrift entitled A Just and True Love: Feminism, Theology and Ethics in a Global Context (University of Notre Dame Press, 2007).